Nichols Family Papers, 1728-1894 Ms 23
Fairfield Museum and History Center
Nichols Family Papers, 1728-1894
Ms 23
Fairfield Museum and History Center
1.5 Linear feet (3 boxes, 134 items, 3 oversize items)
Nichols family
Nichols, Samuel Allen, 1790-1864
Nichols, Susan Warner, 1828-1911
Scambler, Jasper
Conditions Governing Access note
There are no restrictions on access to this collection.
Custodial History note
The items in this collection were given to the library by E. Perkins Nichols, the estate of Elizabeth H. Nichols and unknown sources.
Biographical/Historical note
The papers in this collection belonged to the descendants of the Nichols family who settled in Stratford, CT in the middle 1600's. As early land holders, many continued as farmers. Others were millers, storekeepers, smithies, shoemakers and school teachers. Samuel Allen Nichols (1789-1864) was a storekeeper and the Town Clerk for Fairfield from 1837-1863. For a published genealogy see: History and Genealogy of Old Fairfield, Vol. I, Part II by Donald Lines Jacobus, Fairfield, CT, 1930.
Scope and Contents note
The collection is housed in three boxes and has three oversize items. Box I, Folder A-C contain deeds. Financial, contractual and probate papers are in Folder D. Folder E contains correspondence, legal papers and certificates. Of particular note is a negro girl contract from Ebenezer Nichols dated 1804. Folder F contains a recipe book and Folder G holds the diaries of John J. Nichols (1838-1922).
Box II contains account books of Peter Nichols and Samuel Allen Nichols (1790-1864). Box III contains diaries and verse books belonging to Susan Warner Nichols (1828-1911).
Oversize Item A is a 1785 illustrated navigation copy book of Jasper Scambler. In Oversize Item B are two account books. Oversize Item C holds Samuel Allen Nichol's account book.
Nichols, Ebenezer; Nichols, Ephraim; Nichols, Peter, fl. 1772-1782; Account books--Connecticut--Fairfield.; Blacksmithing--Connecticut--Fairfield.; Diaries.; Genealogy.; General stores--Connecticut--Fairfield.; Merchants--Connecticut--Fairfield.; Navigation--Early works to 1800.; Probate records--Connecticut--Fairfield.; Real property--Connecticut--Fairfield County.; Receipts(financial records); Shoe industry--Connecticut--Fairfield.; Slaves--Connecticut.; Weaving--Connecticut--New Milford.; Women--Connecticut--Fairfield--Diaries.; Writs--Connecticut.
- Box I, 7 folders
  - Deeds, 1728-1788; Folder A; 22 items
    Other Finding Aids note
    See the box for a more detailed list of items in the folder.
  - Deeds to Ebenezer Nichols, 1789-1798; Folder B; 23 items
  - Deeds, 1799-1868; Folder C; 25 items
  - Financial, Contractual and Probate Papers, Folder D; 34 items
  - Correspondence, Legal Papers, and Certificates, Folder E; 14 items
  - Books, Folder F; 2 items
    - Recipe book, n.d.
    - E. H. Nichol's receipt book, 1866-1868
  - Diaries, Folder G; 5 items
    - John J. Nichols, 1861, 1867, 1882, 1889-1890; 4 items
    - Martha Nichols, 1867
- Box II, 3 folders
  - Account books of Peter Nichols, 1771-1777; Folder A; 2 items; The first 18 pages are 1760-1765 accounts of Joseph Wheeler, a New Milford weaver.
  - Account book and diary, Folder B; 2 items
    - Account book of Samuel Allen Nichols, 1835-1836
    - Diary of Samuel Allen Nichols, a journey from Fairfield to Geneva, NY and return
  - Papers from Samuel Allen Nichol's account book, 1827-1834; Folder C
- Box III, 5 folders
  - Diary of Susan Warner Nichols, 1886; Folder A
  - Diaries of Susan Warner Nichols, 1850, 1903, 1904, 1909; Folder B; 4 items
  - Friendship books of Susan Warner Nichols, 1851, n.d.; Folder C; 2 items
  - Miscellaneous, Folder D
    - Nichols genealogy chart
    - Photocopy of letter from F. W. Seward regarding Captain Hanford Nicholls, 1862
  - Diaries and Marriage Certificate, Folder F; 3 items
    - Diaries of George W. Nichols, 1848, 1849; 2 items
    - Marriage certificate, 1839
- Oversize Item A
  Biographical/Historical note
  This is a 2,000 page copy book with many hand-drawn diagrams and water color illustrations. A genealogy chart in Box III, Folder D, connects the Nichols and Scambler families.
  - The Elements of Navigation by Jasper Scambler, educated in the Royal Mathematical School, Christ's Hospital, London, MDCCLXXXV, 1785
- Oversize Item B, 2 items
  - Ephraim Nichols account book for shoe repairs, 1820-1829
  - Henry Nichols blacksmith account book, 1839-1860
- Oversize Item C
  - Samuel Allen Nichols account book, 1827-1834
    Custodial History note
    This item is from accession number L88.Aug.17.